Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Lily Emmet Cushing papers
1929-1972
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Cushing, Lily Emmet
4.0 linear feet
The papers of painter Lily Emmet Cushing date from 1929 to 1972 and measure 4.0 linear feet. Found within the papers are biographical material; letters from friends including Henri Bernstein, Alfred M. Frankfurter, Katharine Graham, Nancy Kefauver, and Walt Kuhn; personal business records including financial material concerning the Maynard Walker Gallery; notes and writings; art work; printed material; and photographs.
Provenance
The Lily Emmet Cushing papers were donated in 1972 by the artist's daughters Alexandra Emmet Schlesinger and Lily Emmet West.
Separated Material
An unrecorded number of exhibition catalogs were removed from the collection and given to the Smithsonian American Art Museum/National Portrait Gallery Art Library in 1977.
Restrictions on Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Biographical Note
Lily Cushing (1909-1969) of New York City was primarily known as a painter of landscapes and still lifes of flowers.
Lily Cushing was born on January 13, 1909 in New York City, the third child of Ethel Cochrane and artist Howard Gardiner Cushing. She studied painting in the studio of Alexandre Jacovleff in Paris from 1926-1927, and with Walt Kuhn in New York City in 1929. Cushing's first solo exhibition was at the Arden Gallery in New York in 1930.
In 1929, Cushing married George Crawford Clark Jr. in Newport, Rhode Island. Following her divorce from Clark, she married William Temple Emmet, Jr. in 1932. They had two daughters, Alexandra and Lily. Cushing's second marriage also ended in divorce. In 1953, she married naval officer Alston M. Boyd in New York.
Cushing's work is in the collections of the Metropolitan Museum of Art, the Museum of Modern Art, the Whitney Museum of American Art, and in the private collections of Paul Mellon, John Hay Whitney, and Joseph P. Kennedy, among others.
Lily Cushing died on September 21, 1969, in Fishers Island, New York.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of painter Lily Emmet Cushing date from 1929 to 1972 and measure 4.0 linear feet. Found within the papers are biographical material; letters from friends including Henri Bernstein, Alfred M. Frankfurter, Katharine Graham, Nancy Kefauver, and Walt Kuhn; personal business records including financial material concerning the Maynard Walker Gallery; notes and writings; art work; printed material; and photographs.
Biographical material consists primarily of address books and lists of addresses, but also includes miscellaneous resumés and a certificate of participation in the Art in the Embassies program. signed by Nancy Kefauver.
Scattered letters received by Cushing are primarily from friends including Henri Bernstein, Alfred M. Frankfurter, Katharine Graham, Nancy Kefauver, and Walt Kuhn. There are also letters concerning the Chinese Women's Anti-Aggression League that benefited the charitable and social welfare organizations of the Chinese Navy.
Personal business records include lists of art work and purchasers, price lists, financial and legal documents, and various receipts, including some for art supplies. Papers concerning the Maynard Walker Gallery include letters discussing sales, invoices, and a ledger listing sales of art work by various artists including Lily Cushing Emmet.
Notes and Writings consist of notebooks containing annotations on miscellaneous topics including household items, painting, plants, and recipes. Miscellaneous notes concern art work, fabric, and furnishings. Typescripts by others concern the genealogy of the Clark family.
Art work consists of a schematic drawing, small oil paintings on masonite, and a commercial printing block of a design by Walt Kuhn.
Printed material consists of clippings, exhibition announcements and catalogs, programs, miscellaneous brochures, picture postcards of scenes in the United States, Europe, and Mexico and of Native Americans.
Photographs are of Cushing, her daughters, her third husband Capt. Alston Boyd, friends and colleagues including Mme. Chiang Kai-Shek, various houses, travel scenes, miscellaneous plants, and of art work. There is also a photograph of Jacqueline Kennedy Onassis.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as 7 series:
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1953-1967 (Box 1; 14 folders)
Series 2: Letters, 1929-1972 (Box 1-2, OV 7; 1.4 linear feet)
Series 3: Personal Business Records, 1934-1969 (Box 2-3, 6; 0.8 linear feet)
Series 4: Notes and Writings, 1955-1969 (Box 3; 23 folders)
Series 5: Art Work, circa 1940 (Box 3, 6; 3 folders)
Series 6: Printed Material, 1930-1968 (Box 3, 6; 30 folders)
Series 7: Photographs, 1940-1968 (Box 3-6; 0.8 linear feet)
Names and Subject Terms
This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following terms:
Subjects:
Chiang, May-ling Soong, 1897-2003; Onassis, Jacqueline Kennedy, 1929-; Maynard Walker Gallery; Zhonghua fu nu fan gong kang E lian he hui
Subjects-Topical:
Art, American--United States; Painters--New York (State)--New York; Women artists
Types of Materials:
Notebooks; Paintings; Photographs; Postcards; Typescripts
Names:
Bernstein, Henri; Frankfurter, Alfred M.; Graham, Katharine, 1917-; Kefauver, Nancy, 1912-1967; Kuhn, Walt, 1877-1949
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Biographical Material, 1953-1967, Series 1:; (Box 1; 14 folders)
  Biographical material consists primarily of address books and address lists. There are also photocopies of Cushing's marriage license with Alston Boyd, miscellaneous resumés, and a certificate of participation in the Art in Embassies program.
  - Photocopies of Marriage License; Miscellaneous Resumés, 1953-1967, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Certificate of Participation in Art in the Embassies Program, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Address Books, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Cushing's Old List of Addresses, undated, (4 folders) (Box 1, Folder 4-7)
  - Cushing's Revised List of Addresses, 1964, (4 folders) (Box 1, Folder 8-11)
  - Miscellaneous Address Lists, 1961-1967, undated, (3 folders) (Box 1, Folder 12-14)
- Letters, 1929-1972, Series 2:; (Box 1-2, OV 7; 1.4 linear feet)
  Scattered letters received by Cushing are primarily from friends including Alfred M. Frankfurter, Katharine Graham, and Nancy Kefauver. Ten letters each received from Walt Kuhn and French playwright Henri Bernstein encourage Cushing in her work and activities. There are single letters from Joseph Alsop, José Ferrer, Jacqueline Kennedy, Henry Cabot Lodge, Tex McCrary, and Arthur Schlesinger. There is also a file of letters concerning the Chinese Women's Anti-Aggression League that benefited the charitable and social welfare organizations of the Chinese Navy
  - Unsigned Letters, undated, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 15-16)
  - Letters from Correspondents with Unknown Surnames, undated, (4 folders) (Box 1, Folder 17-20)
  - Letters from Correspondents with Surnames "A" - "B," undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Letters from Correspondents with Surnames "C," undated, (6 folders) (Box 1, Folder 22-27)
  - Letters from Correspondents with Surnames "D" - "E," undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Letters from Correspondents with Surnames "F," undated (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Letters from Correspondents with Surnames "G," undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Letters from Correspondents with Surnames "H," undated (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Letters from Correspondents with Surnames "I" - "J," undated (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Letters from Correspondents with Surnames "K," undated, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 33-34)
  - Letters from Correspondents with Surnames "L," undated, (3 folders) (Box 1, Folder 35-37)
  - Letters from Correspondents with Surnames "M" - "O," undated (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Letters from Correspondents with Surnames "P" - "R," undated (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Letters from Correspondents with Surnames "S," undated (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Letters from Correspondents with Surnames "T," undated (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Letters from Correspondents with Surnames "W," undated (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Letters from Correspondents with Surnames "Y," (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Letters, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Letters, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Letters, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Letters, 1945, (3 folders) (Box 1, Folder 47-49)
  - Letters, 1948-1955 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Letters, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Letters, 1957, (3 folders)(Oversized Material Housed in OV 7) (Box 1, Folder 52-55)
  - Letters, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Letters, (3 folders) (Box 1, Folder 57-59)
  - Letters, 1960, (8 folders) (Box 1, Folder 60-67)
  - Letters, 1961, (10 folders) (Box 2, Folder 1-10)
  - Letters, 1962, (5 folders) (Box 2, Folder 11-15)
  - Letters, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Letters, 1964, (3 folders) (Box 2, Folder 17-19)
  - Letters, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 17-19)
  - Letters, 1965, (5 folders) (Box 2, Folder 20-24)
  - Letters, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Letters, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Letters, 1968, (3 folders) (Box 2, Folder 27-29)
  - Letters, 1969-1972 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Letters from Walt Kuhn, 1929-1943 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Letters from Henri Bernstein, 1945, undated, (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 32-33)
  - Letters Concerning the Chinese Women's Anti-Aggression League, 1959-1960 (Box 2, Folder 34-39)
  - An Oversized Blueprint and Schematic Design for the Decoration of Ship Cabins, 1957, from Box 1, Folder 55 (Box OV 7)
- Personal Business Records, 1934-1969, Series 3:; (Box 2-3, 6; 0.8 linear feet)
  Personal business records include lists of art work and purchasers, price lists, benefits reports from the will of Alexander Cochrane, stock reports, mortgage loan records, banking records, income tax records, insurance records, framing and shipping invoices, and receipts for art supplies, household and landscaping work, automobile repairs, and travel to Greece, Rhodes, Italy, Mallorca, and Mexico. Financial material concerning the Maynard Walker Gallery includes letters discussing sales, invoices, and a ledger listing sales of art work by various artists including Lily Cushing Emmet, John Edward Heliker, Walt Kuhn, Doris Lee, Frank Mechau, Dudley Morris, Andree Ruellan, Lee Townsend, and J. Alden Weir.
  - Invoices and Letters from the Maynard Walker Gallery, 1954-1967, undated, (12 folders) (Box 2, Folder 40-51)
  - Lists of Art Work and Purchasers, 1957-1969, (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 52-53)
  - Art Work Price Lists, 1963-1969, (3 folders) (Box 2, Folder 54-56)
  - Benefits Reports from the Will of Alexander Cochrane, 1961-1965, (3 folders) (Box 2, Folder 57-59)
  - Stock Reports, 1954-1967, (4 folders) (Box 2, Folder 60-63)
  - Mortgage Loan Records, 1949-1959 (Box 2, Folder 64)
  - Banking Records, 1956-1964, (4 folders) (Box 2, Folder 65-68)
  - Income Tax Records, 1956-1965, (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 69-70)
  - Insurance Records, 1955-1964, (4 folders) (Box 2, Folder 71-74)
  - Framing and Shipping Invoices, 1963-1968 (Box 2, Folder 75)
  - Gou Shipping Company Invoices, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 76)
  - Household Receipts, 1959-1966, undated, (5 folders) (Box 3, Folder 1-5)
  - Receipts for Landscaping, 1964-1968 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Receipts for Art Supplies, 1960-1967, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Automobile Receipts, 1960-1966, (2 folders) (Box 3, Folder 8-9)
  - Receipts from Travel to Greece and Rhodes, 1960-1961, (2 folders) (Box 3, Folder 10-11)
  - Receipts for Travel to Italy, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Receipts for Travel to Mallorca (Spain), 1961-1967 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Receipts for Travel to Mexico, 1961-1968 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Miscellaneous Receipts, 1956-1968, undated, (2 folders) (Box 3, Folder 15-16)
  - Oversized Maynard Walker Gallery Ledger Listing Sales of Art Work by Various Artists including Cushing, 1934-1957 (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Notes and Writings, 1955-1969, Series 4:; (Box 3; 23 folders)
  Notes and Writings consist of notebooks containing annotations on miscellaneous topics including household items, painting, plants, and recipes. Miscellaneous notes concern art work, fabric, and furnishings. Typescripts by others concern the genealogy of the Clark family.
  - Notebook Containing Annotations in Chinese, undated (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Notebook Concerning Miscellaneous Topics, undated (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Notebook "Some of Bertha's Recipes," undated (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Notebook "Recipes and Nostrums," 1955-1966, undated, (3 folders) (Box 3, Folder 20-22)
  - Notebook: "Want Lists, E. M. Club Tayloring, and San Francisco House," 1958-1966 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Notebook Containing Annotations in Greek, 1960-1961 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Notebook Concerning Household Items and Notes on Painting, 1960-1961, (5 folders) (Box 3, Folder 25-29)
  - Notebook: "Stowage," 1961 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Notebook: "Correspondence from S. F.," 1965-1966 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Notebook: "Plant Book - 2 Belmont, S.F.," 1966 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Notebook Concerning Miscellaneous Topics, 1969, undated (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Miscellaneous Notes on Art Work, 1961, undated (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Miscellaneous Notes on Fabric and Furnishings, undated (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Miscellaneous Notes, undated (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Notes and Writings by Others: "Notes by Al," undated (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Notes and Writings by Others: Typescript "Genealogy of Winifred Stockbridge Bartlett Clark," undated (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Notes and Writings by Others: Typescript: "Three with a History" by Winifred Shaw-Clark, undated (Box 3, Folder 39)
- Art Work, circa 1940, Series 5:; (Box 3, 6; 3 folders)
  Art work consists of a schematic drawing with annotations concerning a painting of flowers, three small oil paintings on masonite depicting portraits of girls and a scene at the beach, and a commercial printing block of a design by Walt Kuhn.
  - Small Oil Paintings on Masonite, undated, (2 folders) (Box 3, Folder 40-41)
  - Commercial Printing Block with Design by Walt Kuhn, undated (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Oversized Schematic Drawing of Flowers in a Vase, undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Printed Material, 1930-1968, Series 6:; (Box 3, 6; 30 folders)
  Printed material consists of clippings, exhibition announcements and catalogs for Cushing, programs, brochures concerning tiger balm, crafts in Mexico, and miscellaneous travel. Picture postcards are of Native Americans, and of scenes in the United States, Europe, and Mexico.
  - Clippings, undated, (Oversized Material Housed in Box 6) (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Clippings, 1930-1944 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Clippings, 1945 (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Clippings, 1946-1947 (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Clippings, 1948-1949 (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Clippings, 1952-1955 (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - Clippings, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Clippings, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - Clippings, 1960, (2 folders)(Oversized Material Housed in Box 6) (Box 3, Folder 51-52)
  - Clippings, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - Clippings, 1962-1968 (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, undated (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1947-1948 (Box 3, Folder 56)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 57)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 58)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 59)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs for Others, 1966-1967 (Box 3, Folder 60)
  - Programs, 1959-1960, undated (Box 3, Folder 61)
  - Brochures Concerning Crafts of Mexico, undated (Box 3, Folder 62)
  - Travel Brochures, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 63)
  - Miscellaneous Brochures, 1959, undated, (Oversized Material Housed in Box 6) (Box 3, Folder 64)
  - Picture Postcards of California, Nevada, and Hawaii, undated (Box 3, Folder 65)
  - Picture Postcards of Miscellaneous Sites in the United States, undated (Box 3, Folder 66)
  - Picture Postcards of Miscellaneous Sites in Europe, undated (Box 3, Folder 67)
  - Picture Postcards of Miscellaneous Sites in Mexico, undated (Box 3, Folder 68)
  - Picture Postcards of Native Americans, undated (Box 3, Folder 69)
  - Fishers Island Telephone Directory, 1964-1965 (Box 3, Folder 70)
  - Miscellaneous Printed Material, 1955-1966, undated (Box 3, Folder 71)
  - Three Oversized Chinese Newspapers, undated, (from Box 3, folder 43) (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Two Oversized Newspaper Clippings, 1960, (from Box 3, Folder 51) (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Oversized Brochure for Tiger Balm, undated, (from Box 3, Folder 64) (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Photographs, 1940-1968, Series 7:; (Box 3-6 linear feet)
  Photographs are of Cushing, her daughters, her third husband Capt. Alston Boyd, friends and colleagues including Mme. Chiang Kai-Shek visiting an exhibition by Cushing, Cushing's homes in San Francisco and Fishers Island, travel scenes, miscellaneous plants, and of art work. There is also a photograph of Jacqueline Kennedy Onassis.
  - Photographs of Lily Cushing, 1947-1966, undated, (2 folders; Oversized Material Housed in Box 6) (Box 3, Folder 72-73)
  - Photographs of Lily Cushing and Capt. Alston Boyd, 1953-1960 (Box 3, Folder 74)
  - Photographs of Capt. Alston Boyd, 1959, undated, (3 folders) (Box 3, Folder 75-77)
  - Photographs of Cushing and Family Members, 1940-1960, undated, (3 folders; Oversized Material Housed in Box 6) (Box 3, Folder 78)
  - Photographs of Cushing with Friends and Colleagues, undated, (2 folders) (Box 4, Folder 1-2)
  - Photographs of Cushing at Unidentified Events, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Photographs of Mme. Chiang Kai-Shek at an Exhibition of Cushing's Art Work, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Photographs of Miscellaneous Friends, undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Photographs of Unidentified Houses, undated, (4 folders)(Oversized Material Housed in Box 6) (Box 4, Folder 6-9)
  - Photographs of the San Francisco House, undated (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Photographs of Fishers Island, 1968, (2 folders) (Box 4, Folder 11-12)
  - Photographs of Mellons' Garden, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Photographs of Mexico and California, undated (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Miscellaneous Travel Photographs, 1954-1962, undated, (3 folders) (Box 4, Folder 15-17)
  - Photographs of Miscellaneous Plants, 1967-1968, undated, (2 folders) (Box 4, Folder 18-19)
  - Photographs of Art Work: Female Figures, undated, (9 folders) (Box 4, Folder 20-28)
  - Photographs of Art Work: Views of New Orleans, undated (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Photographs of Art Work: Views of New York, undated, (2 folders) (Box 4, Folder 30-31)
  - Photographs of Art Work: "Rome Morning," undated (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Photographs of Art Work: Views of Rhodes, undated, (4 folders) (Box 4, Folder 33-36)
  - Photographs of Art Work: Views of Taiwan, undated, (3 folders) (Box 5, Folder 1-3)
  - Photographs of Art Work: Miscellaneous Towns and Buildings, undated, (2 folders) (Box 5, Folder 4-5)
  - Photographs of Art Work: Tropical Scenes, undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Photographs of Art Work: Forests and Parks, undated, (2 folders) (Box 5, Folder 7-8)
  - Photographs of Art Work: Flowers in Vases, undated, (2 folders) (Box 5, Folder 9-10)
  - Photographs of Art Work: Miscellaneous Plants, undated, (2 folders) (Box 5, Folder 11-12)
  - Photographs of Art Work: "Hat Rack," undated (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Oversized Photograph of Lily Cushing, circa 1960, (from Box 3, Folder 72) (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Three Oversized Photographs of Cushing and her Daughters, circa 1960, (from Box 3, Folder 79) (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Oversized Aerial Photograph of Houses, undated, (from Box 4, Folder 7) (Box 6, Folder 4)